Niklas Edvall - CV - January 9, 2023

niklasedvall@gmail.com 🎓 Bromma, Stockholm



Introduction

Licensed audiologist since 2013 with an interest in signal processing and optimization of both technical and clinical solutions. I am a PhD candidate at the Karolinska Institute since April 2019, scheduled to complete my PhD in March 2023. I gravitated towards research as I thrive surrounded by colleagues with a wide variety of expertise, in an environment that provides novel challenges on a regular basis. Whenever possible, I am happy to involve myself in adjacent projects to exchange experiences, knowledge and procedures. During my PhD I have advanced my knowledge in auditory neuroscience, study design and signal processing but also developed competence on setting up a stable pipeline for data collection, processing and analysis. Teaching experience from lecturing, training and supervising students, colleagues and the general public, has equipped me with a flexible toolbox for communicating audiological concepts and I am never happier than when someone is interested to listen!

Skills

MS Office	••••
Matlab	$\bullet \bullet \bullet \bullet \circ$
R	
JMP	
LaTex	$\bullet \bullet \bullet \circ \circ$
Python	$\bullet \bullet \bullet \circ \circ$
git	$\bullet \bullet \bullet \circ \circ$
Swedish	
English	••••

■ Invited speaker

Bellman & Symfon, Audionova, Eartech, Hörselskadades Riksförbund, Hörselvården Region Sörmland, STAF

🖋 Leisure

Long-distance cycling and walking the dog.

? References

Available on request.

Previous Employment

2019 - March 2023: Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm

PhD candidate with the research project: Objective tinnitus diagnostics using neuroimaging techniques.

2017 - 2019: Region Stockholm

Research assistant affiliated with Karolinska Institutet.

2015 - 2017: Karolinska Institutet, Stockholm

Research assistant in the lab for experimental audiology, responsible for data collection within the Swedish Tinnitus Outreach Project (STOP).

2013 - 2015: Hörseltjänst Malmö

Licensed Audiologist, diagnostics and technical rehabilitation.

Education

2023: PhD in auditory neuroscience (scheduled 2023-04-24).

2015: Master of Medical Science, Audiology (MMSc), Lund University.

2013: Bachelor of Medical Science, Audiology, Lund University.

• Other

- Recieved research grants from Hörselforskningsfonden (2020) and the Tysta Skolan foundation (2020 & 2021).
- Member of the COST network TINNET with the aim to understand the heterogeneity of tinnitus (2015-2018).
- Poster presentation at the TRI (2018), ARO (2020) and CHScom (2022) conferences.
- Exchange semester at the University of Melbourne (2014).

Niklas Edvall - Publications

- Edvall, N. K., G. Mehraei, M. Claeson, A. Lazar, J. Bulla, C. Leineweber, I. Uhlén, B. Canlon, and C. R. Cederroth (2022). "Alterations in auditory brainstem response distinguish occasional and constant tinnitus". *The Journal of Clinical Investigation*, e155094. DOI: 10.1172/JCI155094.
- Genitsaridi, E., T. Kypraios, **N. K. Edvall**, N. Trpchevska, B. Canlon, D. J. Hoare, C. R. Cederroth, and D. A. Hall (2021). "The spatial percept of tinnitus is associated with hearing asymmetry: Subgroup comparisons". *Progress in Brain Research* 263, pp. 59–80. DOI: 10.1016/bs.pbr.2021.04.006.
- Cederroth, C. R., A. Lugo, N. K. Edvall, A. Lazar, J.-A. Lopez-Escamez, J. Bulla, I. Uhlen, D. J. Hoare, D. M. Baguley, B. Canlon, and S. Gallus (2020). "Association between Hyperacusis and Tinnitus". *Journal of Clinical Medicine* 9.8, E2412. DOI: 10.3390/jcm9082412.
- Lugo, A., N. K. Edvall, A. Lazar, G. Mehraei, J.-A. Lopez-Escamez, J. Bulla, I. Uhlen, B. Canlon, S. Gallus, and C. R. Cederroth (2020). "Relationship between headaches and tinnitus in a Swedish study". *Scientific Reports* 10.1, p. 8494. DOI: 10.1038/s41598-020-65395-1.
- Trpchevska, N., J. Bulla, M. Prada Hellberg, N. K. Edvall, A. Lazar, G. Mehraei, I. Uhlen, W. Schlee, B. Canlon, S. Gallus, J. A. Lopez-Escamez, and C. R. Cederroth (2020). "Sex-Dependent Aggregation of Tinnitus in Swedish Families". *Journal of Clinical Medicine* 9.12, E3812. DOI: 10.3390/jcm9123812.
- Edvall, N. K., E. Gunan, E. Genitsaridi, A. Lazar, G. Mehraei, M. Billing, M. Tullberg, J. Bulla, J. Whitton, B. Canlon, D. A. Hall, and C. R. Cederroth (2019). "Impact of Temporomandibular Joint Complaints on Tinnitus-Related Distress". Frontiers in Neuroscience 13, p. 879. DOI: 10.3389/fnins.2019.00879.
- Genitsaridi, E., M. Partyka, S. Gallus, J. A. Lopez-Escamez, M. Schecklmann, M. Mielczarek, N. Trpchevska, J. L. Santacruz, S. Schoisswohl, C. Riha, M. Lourenco, R. Biswas, N. Liyanage, C. R. Cederroth, P. Perez-Carpena, J. Devos, T. Fuller, N. K. Edvall, M. P. Hellberg, A. D'Antonio, S. Gerevini, M. Sereda, A. Rein, T. Kypraios, D. J. Hoare, A. Londero, R. Pryss, W. Schlee, and D. A. Hall (2019). "Standardised profiling for tinnitus research: The European School for Interdisciplinary Tinnitus Research Screening Questionnaire (ESIT-SQ)". Hearing Research 377, pp. 353–359. DOI: 10.1016/j.heares.2019.02.017.
- Tserga, E., T. Nandwani, N. K. Edvall, J. Bulla, P. Patel, B. Canlon, C. R. Cederroth, and D. M. Baguley (2019). "The genetic vulnerability to cisplatin ototoxicity: a systematic review". *Scientific Reports* 9.1, p. 3455. DOI: 10.1038/s41598-019-40138-z.
- Fuller, T. E., H. F. Haider, D. Kikidis, A. Lapira, B. Mazurek, A. Norena, S. Rabau, R. Lardinois, C. R. Cederroth, N. K. Edvall, P. G. Brueggemann, S. N. Rosing, A. Kapandais, D. Lungaard, D. J. Hoare, and R. F. F. Cima (2017). "Different Teams, Same Conclusions? A Systematic Review of Existing Clinical Guidelines for the Assessment and Treatment of Tinnitus in Adults". Frontiers in Psychology 8, p. 206. DOI: 10.3389/fpsyg.2017.00206.
- Maas, I. L., P. Brüggemann, T. Requena, J. Bulla, N. K. Edvall, J. V. B. Hjelmborg, A. J. Szczepek, B. Canlon, B. Mazurek, J. A. Lopez-Escamez, and C. R. Cederroth (2017). "Genetic susceptibility to bilateral tinnitus in a Swedish twin cohort". Genetics in Medicine: Official Journal of the American College of Medical Genetics 19.9, pp. 1007–1012. DOI: 10.1038/gim.2017.4.
- Schlee, W., D. A. Hall, N. K. Edvall, B. Langguth, B. Canlon, and C. R. Cederroth (2017). "Visualization of Global Disease Burden for the Optimization of Patient Management and Treatment". Frontiers in Medicine 4, p. 86. DOI: 10.3389/fmed.2017.00086.
- Hall, D. A., H. Haider, A. J. Szczepek, P. Lau, S. Rabau, J. Jones-Diette, A. Londero, N. K. Edvall, C. R. Cederroth, M. Mielczarek, T. Fuller, A. Batuecas-Caletrio, P. Brueggemen, D. M. Thompson, A. Norena, R. F. F. Cima, R. L. Mehta, and B. Mazurek (2016). "Systematic review of outcome domains and instruments used in clinical trials of tinnitus treatments in adults". Trials 17.1, p. 270. DOI: 10.1186/s13063-016-1399-9.
- Müller, K., N. K. Edvall, E. Idrizbegovic, R. Huhn, R. Cima, V. Persson, C. Leineweber, H. Westerlund, B. Langguth, W. Schlee, B. Canlon, and C. R. Cederroth (2016). "Validation of Online Versions of Tinnitus Questionnaires Translated into Swedish". Frontiers in Aging Neuroscience 8, p. 272. DOI: 10.3389/fnagi.2016.00272.
- Rance, G., D. Chisari, N. Edvall, and F. Cameron (2016). "Functional hearing deficits in children with Type 1 diabetes". Diabetic Medicine: A Journal of the British Diabetic Association 33.9, pp. 1268–1274. DOI: 10.1111/dme.13086.
- Hiselius, P., N. Edvall, and D. Reimers (2015). "To measure the impact of hearing protectors on the perception of speech in noise". *International Journal of Audiology* 54 Suppl 1, S3–8. DOI: 10.3109/14992027.2014.973539.